Guide to the Grace Vance Erickson Papers 1863-1958
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Grace Vance Erickson Papers
1863-1958
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 286
Erickson, Grace V. (Grace Vance), 1873-1962
2 linear feet of shelf space
Grace Vance Erickson was a Helena, Montana, area, amateur historian and the wife of Governor John Edward Erickson. This collection consists of biographical information; general correspondence, including personal letters from J. E. Erickson; miscellaneous correspondence; diaries; press releases; speeches; subject files containing notes on her historic research; miscellany, including an autograph book, a guestbook, and scrapbooks including one on the Community Council of Kalispell and the Women's Committee of the Council of National Defense; and clippings. The collection also includes information on A. M. Vance, Grace Vance Erickson's father.
Biographical Note:
Grace Vance was born around 1873 in LaGrange, Iowa, the daughter of Andrew M. and Ellen Cooper Vance. She received a degree in literature from the University of Michigan. She moved to Choteau, Montana, in the mid 1890s to work as a teacher. In June of 1898 she married John E. Erickson, a Choteau attorney. The couple moved to Kalispell in 1915. John E. Erickson served two full terms as Governor (1924-1933) and, following his re-election to a third term, resigned to replace Thomas J. Walsh, in the U.S. Senate. He was replaced by James W. Murray in 1934. Grace Vance Erickson was active in the Democratic Party, the Montana Natural History Association, the Daughters of the American Revolution, and the Presbyterian Church. She was an active amateur historian, anthropologist and archaeologist and was involved with the preservation of historic sites. She died July 16, 1962.
Papers. 1863-1958. 2 linear feet. These papers consist of general correspondence, including personal letters from J. E. Erickson; miscellaneous correspondence; diaries concerning Grace Vance Erickson's life in Iowa, at the University of Michigan, and as the wife of the governor; press releases; speeches; subject files regarding her work as an amateur historian; writings; miscellany including a scrapbook concerning the Community Council of Kalispell and the Women's Committee of the Council of National Defense; and clippings.
by series
Acquisition information available upon request
Photographs, and artifacts transferred to the Photo Archives and Museum, respectively.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Historic sites--Montana
Benson's Landing (Mont.)
Bitterroot River Valley (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Fergus County (Mont.)
Kalispell (Mont.)--Politics and government
St. Ignatius (Mont.)
Yellowstone City (Mont.)
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Biographical Material
  - Chronologies, genealogical chart, n.d., 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- General Correspondence
  - A - Z (correspondents include: J. E. Erickson, Belle Fligelman, S. H. Knowles, Jeannette Rankin, Al Vance, A. M. Vance), n.d., 1890-1958 (Box-folder 1 / 2-4)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  - Neither from nor to Grace Vance Erickson (correspondents include: Ellen Erickson, J. E. Erickson, Al Vance, A. M. Vance), 1902-1929 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Diaries
  - Diary (re: life in Iowa), 1889 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Diary (re: life at the University of Michigan), 1891-1902 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Diaries (re: life as wife of Governor J. E. Erickson), 1925-1926, 1932 (Box-folder 1 / 8-9)
- Press Releases
  - Press Notice (re: recitals), n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 10)
- Speeches
  - Eureka Women's Club (re: women's role in World War II), 1918 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Subject Files
  - Frederick Conrad, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - William Davenport, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Fergus County, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - First Families of Flathead (re: Father Pierre J. De Smet and St. Ignatius Mission), n.d., 1930-1941 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Governor's Mansion, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Helena (re: Atlas Block, Pioneer Cabin), n.d., 1939-1957 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Historic preservation, 1930-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - James Jackson, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Livingston (re: Benson's Landing, Ghost City and Yellowstone City) (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Historic sites in Montana, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - St. Peter's Mission, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - David Thompson, n.d., 1923-1940 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
- Writings
  - "A Star in the East", n.d., 1952 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
- Miscellany
  - Autograph Book, 1882-1889 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Ephemera (including certificates, Christmas cards, invitations, name cards, passport, and programs), n.d., 1891-1951 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Ephemera (re: Ellen Erickson, J. E. Erickson, and A. M. Vance, 1863-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Guestbook, 1929-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Montana Oil Conservation Board, n.d., 1951 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Oro Fino Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1890-1914 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Scrapbook "Historical Expeditions", 1925-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Scrapbook (re: Community Council of Kalispell and the Women's Committee of the Council of National Defense): See Box 3 (Box-folder 2 /)
  - Scrapbook (re: Community Council of Kalispell and the Women's Committee of the Council of National Defense), 1917-1918, 1934-1939 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Scrapbook "Touring the Circuit", 1928 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Scrapbook of Wives of the Cabinet Officers, 1933-1935 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
- Clippings
  - Clippings (re: Grace Vance Ericksone, J. E. Erickson, Al Vance, and A. M. Vance), n.d., 1935-1949 (Box-folder 4 / 3)